Edward F. Edinger Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edward F. Edinger Papers 1550-2016 1951-1998
MSS86117
Edinger, Edward F.
3,100 items
15 containers plus 1 oversize
5.8 linear feet
2 digital files (865.2MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Jungian analyst. Writings, lectures, correspondence, notes, photographs, military records, slides, digital files, printed matter, and other papers pertaining to Edinger's career as a Jungian analyst.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Edinger, Edward F.; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882.; Harding, M. Esther (Mary Esther), 1888-1971.; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961.
Subjects
Alchemy--Psychological aspects.; Archetype (Psychology); Dreams.; Ego (Psychology); Gnosticism.; Image of God.; Imagery (Psychology); Individuation (Psychology); Jungian psychology--Religious aspects.; Jungian psychology.; Literature--Psychological aspects.; Mythology, Greek--Psychological aspects.; Mythology--Psychological aspects.; Philosophy, Ancient--Psychological aspects.; Philosophy--Psychological aspects.; Psychoanalysis and literature.; Psychoanalysis and philosophy.; Psychoanalysis and religion.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychology, Religious.; Psychotherapy.; Religion--Psychological aspects.; Schizophrenia.; Subconsciousness.; Symbolism (Psychology); Whole and parts (Psychology)
Titles
Edward F. Edinger Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Jungian analysts.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Edward F. Edinger, Jungian analyst, were given to the Library of Congress by Dianne D. Cordic in 2016 and Susan McGuire in 2020 and 2021.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Audiovisual material has been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Some issues of Quadrant have been transferred to the Serial and Government Publications Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as parts of the Edward F. Edinger Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Technical Requirements
The digital materials consist of two audio files in .wav formats.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of Edward F. Edinger. Reference copies were created from the original digital media. Advanced notice is required for access to digital content; consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Online Content
The papers of Edward F. Edinger are available on the Library of Congress Web site at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000119. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to confsult the online edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1922, Dec. 13 Born, Cedar Rapids, Iowa
1946 M. D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1947 1949 Medical officer, United States Army, Fort Sam Houston, San Antonio, Tex.; Washington, D.C.; and Panama
1951 Began analysis with M. Esther Harding, N.Y.
1962 Founding member, C. G. Jung Institute of New York and C. G. Jung Foundation of New York, N.Y.
1968 1979 President, C. G. Jung Institute of New York
1972 Published Ego and Archetype: Individuation and the Religious Function of the Psyche. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons
1978 Published Melville's Moby-Dick: A Jungian Commentary: An American Nekyia. New York: New Directions Publishing
1979 circa 1998 Analyst, faculty member, and supervisor, C. G. Jung Institute of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, Calif.
1985 Published Anatomy of the Psyche: Alchemical Symbolism in Psychotherapy. La Salle, Ill.: Open Court Publishing Co.
1987 Published Christian Archetype: A Jungian Commentary on the Life of Christ. Toronto: Inner City Books
1990 Published Goethe's Faust: Notes for a Jungian Commentary. Toronto: Inner City Books Published Living Psyche: A Jungian Analysis in Pictures. Wilmette, Ill.: Chiron Publications
1994 Published Transformation of Libido: A Seminar on C. G. Jung's Symbols of Transformation. Los Angeles: C. G. Jung Bookstore
1996 Published New God-Image: A Study of Jung's Key Letters Concerning the Evolution of the Western God-Image. Wilmette, Ill.: Chiron Publications
1998, July 17 Died, Los Angeles, Calif.
1999 Publication of Archetype of the Apocalypse: A Jungian Study of the Book of Revelation. Chicago: Open Court Publishing Co.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edward F. Edinger (1922-1998) span the years 1550-2016, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 1998. The collection relates primarily to Edinger's career as a leading Jungian analyst. He was known for his ability to elucidate C. G. Jung's ideas and concepts in a simple and precise manner, making Jung's work more accessible. The papers also provide insight into Edinger's own theoretical work, including his belief that modern man's psychological disorientation was a result of the loss of a core religious mythology, and his interest in the therapeutic role of alchemy, literature, philosophy, and religion. The collection consists of writings, lectures, correspondence, notes, photographs, military records, slides, digital files, printed matter, and other material. The papers are in English and arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
The majority of the papers comprise Edinger's lectures and writings. Most of his books are based on edited transcripts of lectures. Topics include alchemy, archetypes, C. G. Jung's work, collective unconscious, Greek mythology and philosophy, individuation, the psyche, psychotherapy, symbols, and the transformation of the God-image. The collection does not include Edinger's entire body of work. Files pertaining to lectures and seminars contain correspondence, handwritten and typed lectures, research material, and transcriptions. Writings include handwritten and typed drafts along with supporting material. Edinger's handwritten edits are found throughout the writings. Additionally, the papers document Edinger's efforts, as president of the New York Association for Analytical Psychology, to plan a memorial meeting to honor C. G. Jung in 1961. Also included are occasional journal entries. Digital files consist of audio recordings of Edinger's funeral service. The two files were originally received on two CDs and complement the funeral service paper file.
The 2020 Addition further documents Edinger’s career as a Jungian analyst. Edinger's writings in the 2020 Addition relate to Gnosticism, the psyche, and Ralph Waldo Emerson. Edinger saw parallels between Emerson and Jung and credits Emerson with the development of the introverted intuition. Also included in the addition are notes pertaining to three reading courses taught by Edinger to deepen the understandings of Jung's work. Edinger's reflections on the courses and Jung are reflected in the notes, and the notes also include supporting material. Copies and reprints of lectures and writings about and by M. Esther Harding and C. G. Jung along with writings by others feature topics such as alchemy, C. G. Jung, collective unconscious, dreams, Gnosticism, Ralph Waldo Emerson, and schizophrenia. Prominently featured in the addition is Jung's emphasis on alchemy as not just mystical philosophy or chemistry, but as the symbolic representation of the process of individuation, the path towards psychological wholeness. The 2021 Addition contains two letters between Edinger and Russel B. Huff and Clifford Rollins relating to the collective unconscious. Attached to the letters are images of Rollin's paintings with descriptions.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and followed by additions, closed material, and oversize material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Colleagues, 1953-1961, 1988-1997 (Box 1)
  - General, 1993-1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
- Fish illustration from dream, circa 1951 (Box 1)
- Franz, Marie-Louise von, memorial, 1998 (Box 1)
- Funeral service, 1998 (Box 1)
- Funeral service, audio file, part 1, 1998, Mss86117_129_03
- Funeral service, audio file, part 2, 1998, Mss86117_129_04
- Gospel of Thomas, undated (Box 1)
- Guild of Pastoral Psychology, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
- Hannah, Barbara, 1952 (Box 1)
- Homage to C. G. Jung on the centennial of his birth, 1975 (Box 1)
- International Association for Analytical Psychology, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
- Interviews, 1983, 1991-1993, 1999, 2004, undated (Box 1)
- Introduction to collection, 2016 (Box 1)
- Lectures and seminars (Box 1)
  - "Apocalypse Archetype," 1995 (Box 1)
    - Folder 1 (Box 1)
    - Folder 2 (Box 1)
  - "Archetypes and the Collective Unconscious," undated (Box 1)
  - "Christian Archetype," 1982 (Box 2)
    - Folder 1 (Box 2)
    - Folder 2 (Box 2)
  - "Freud's Contribution to Jungian Psychotherapy," 1956 (Box 2)
  - "History of Analytical Psychology and Its Relation to Other Schools of Psychotherapy," 1957 (Box 2)
  - "Individuation Symbolism in the Old Testament," 1979 (Box 2)
  - "Jungian Community," 1995 (Box 2)
  - "Jungian Theory of the Psyche," undated (Box 2)
  - "Jung's Aion" (Box 2)
    - First semester, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Folder 1 (Box 2)
      - Folder 2 (Box 2)
    - Second semester, 1989 (Box 2)
      - Folder 1 (Box 2)
      - Folder 2 (Box 2)
  - "Jung's Mysterium Coniunctionis," first semester, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Folder 1 (Box 3)
    - Folder 2 (Box 3)
    - Folder 3 (Box 3)
  - "Jung's Psychology of Religion and Culture," 1965 (Box 3)
    - Folder 1 (Box 3)
    - Folder 2 (Box 3)
  - "On the Relation Between Personal and Archetypal Factors in Psychological Development," 1962 (Box 3)
  - "Paracelsus and Individuation," 1994 (Box 3)
    - Folder 1 (Box 3)
    - Folder 2 (Box 3)
  - "Psychiatric Nursing," 1953 (Box 3)
  - "Psychological Approach to Gnosticism and Early Christianity," 1994 (Box 4)
    - Folder 1 (Box 4)
    - Folder 2 (Box 4)
    - Folder 3 (Box 4)
    - Folder 4 (Box 4)
    - Folder 5 (Box 4)
    - Folder 6 (Box 4)
  - "Psychological Approach to Goethe's Faust," 1990 (Box 4)
    - Folder 1 (Box 4)
    - Folder 2 (Box 4)
  - "Psychological Approach to Greek Mythology," 1974 (Box 5)
    - Folder 1 (Box 5)
    - Folder 2 (Box 5)
    - Folder 3 (Box 5)
    - Folder 4 (Box 5)
  - "Psychological Approach to Greek Philosophy," undated (Box 5)
    - Folder 1 (Box 5)
    - Folder 2 (Box 5)
    - Folder 3 (Box 5)
  - "Psychological Approach to the Old Testament" (Box 5)
    - First semester, 1980 (Box 5)
      - Folder 1 (Box 5)
      - Folder 2 (Box 6)
      - Folder 3 (Box 6)
      - Folder 4 (Box 6)
    - Lecture series, 1985 (Box 6)
      - Folder 1 (Box 6)
      - Folder 2 (Box 6)
  - "Psychological Meaning of Greek Mythology," 1974 (Box 6)
  - "Psychology of C. G. Jung," 1958 (Box 6)
    - Folder 1 (Box 6)
    - Folder 2 (Box 6)
    - Folder 3 (Box 7)
  - "Psychology of Inflation and Alienation," 1964 (Box 7)
  - "Psychotherapy and Alchemy" (Box 7)
    - Academic year (Box 7)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
        - First semester (Box 7)
        - Second semester (Box 7)
      - 1980 (Box 7)
    - Programs, 1968, 1976 (Box 7)
  - "Role of Myth," 1957 (Box 7)
  - "Significance of Analytical Psychology for Psychiatry and Psychotherapy," 1967 (Box 7)
  - "Some Manifestations of the Transference Phenomenon," 1957 (Box 7)
  - "Symbolic Life," undated (Box 7)
  - "Symbolism in Jungian Psychology," 1960 (Box 7)
  - "Theology and Psychiatry," 1954 (Box 7)
  - "Tribute to Freud from the Jungian Viewpoint," 1956 (Box 7)
  - "Vocation of Depth Psychotherapy," 1983, 1995 (Box 7)
- Medical license, 1959 (Box 7)
- Medicine, 1985 (Box 7)
- Memorial meeting to honor C. G. Jung, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Folder 1 (Box 8)
  - Folder 2 (Box 8)
- Military records, 1942-1949 (Box 8)
- Miscellany, 1948-1954, 1960, 1967-1973, 1979, undated (Box 8)
- Noll, Richard, 1994-1996 (Box 8)
- Notes, 1950-1977, 1998, undated (Box 8)
  - Folder 1 (Box 8)
  - Folder 2 (Box 8)
- Reviews of Edinger's writings, 1998-2000 (Box 8)
- Slides, 1958, 1977-1980, undated (Box 8)
- Tarot, undated (Box 9)
- Tributes to Edinger, 1998-1999 (Box 9)
- Wheelwright, Joseph B., 1964, 1973 (Box 9)
- Writings (Box 9)
  - Articles and papers (Box 9)
    - "Collective Unconscious as Manifested in Psychosis," 1955 (Box 9)
    - "Helen of Troy," 1977, 1990 (Box 9)
    - "Outline of Analytical Psychology," 1960, 1968 (Box 9)
    - "Paracelsus and the Age of Aquarius," 1996 (Box 9)
    - "Philosopher's Stone: A Symbol of Individuation," undated (Box 9)
    - Printed copies, 1955-1976, 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Psychotherapy and Alchemy: A Study of the Process of Psychotherapy as Symbolized by the Operations of Alchemy," 1967 (Box 9)
    - "Romeo and Juliet: A Coniunctio Drama," circa 1978 (Box 9)
    - "Some Reflections on Jung's Essay a Psychological Approach to the Dogma of the Trinity," undated (Box 9)
    - "Trinity and Quaternity," undated (Box 9)
    - "Wholeness Lost and Found: The Ego-Self Relation as Revealed in Shakespeare's Measure for Measure," circa 1992 (Box 9)
  - Book reviews (Box 10)
    - C. G. Jung: His Myth in Our Times by Marie-Louise von Franz, translated by William H. Kennedy, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Memories, Dreams, Reflections by C. G. Jung, recorded and edited by Aniela Jaffe, translated by Richard and Clara Winston, 1963 (Box 10)
    - Nietzsche's Zarathustra: Notes of the Seminar Given in 1934-1939 by C. G. Jung, edited by James L. Jarrett, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
    - Psychology and Alchemy, Volume 12 of the Collected Works of C. G. Jung translated by R. F. C. Hull, 1954 (Box 10)
    - Self in Psychotic Process: Its Symbolization in Schizophrenia by John Weir Perry, 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Books (Box 10)
    - Apocalypse Archetype: A Jungian Study of the Book of Revelation, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Christian Archetype: A Jungian Commentary on the Life of Christ, 1987 (Box 10)
      - Folder 1 (Box 10)
      - Folder 2 (Box 10)
    - Goethe's Faust: Notes for a Jungian Commentary, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Living Psyche: A Jungian Analysis in Pictures, 1973-1978, 1990, 2000-2004 (Box 10)
      - Folder 1 (Box 10)
      - Folder 2 (Box 11)
      - Folder 3 (Box 11)
      - Folder 4 (Box 11)
      - Folder 5 (Box 11)
    - Mysterium Coniunctionis, abridged by Edinger, undated (Box 11)
    - New God-Image: A Study of Jung's Key Letters Concerning the Evolution of the Western God-Image, 1951-1960, 1991-1996 (Box 11)
      - Folder 1 (Box 11)
      - Folder 2 (Box 11)
      - Folder 3 (Box 12)
      - Folder 4 (Box 12)
      - Folder 5 (Box 12)
      - Folder 6 (Box 12)
    - "Opus of Alchemy: A Psychological Commentary on the Emerald Tablet of Hermes," unpublished, 1976, undated (Box 12)
      - Folder 1 (Box 12)
      - Folder 2 (Box 12)
    - Transformation of Libido: A Seminar on C. G. Jung's Symbols of Transformation, 1994 (Box 12)
- 2020 Addition (Box 13)
  - Alchemical treatises (Box 13)
    - Rosary of the Philosophers (Box 13)
      - English translation, Ferguson manuscript 210, 18th century (Box 13)
      - M. Esther Harding's photostatic copy, 1550 (Box 13)
    - Splendor Solis by Solomon Trismosin, K. Paul, Trench, Trubner and Co. publication, 1920 (Box 13)
  - Basilides, Plato, and Socrates, undated (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 13)
  - Guild of Pastoral Psychology, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Harding, M. Esther (Box 13)
    - "The Anima and Animus: A Curtain Lecture," paper, 1952 (Box 13)
    - Papers from the Second Island Conference Held in Honor of Dr. Esther Harding's Eightieth Birthday, 1968 (Box 13)
    - A Short Review of Dr. Jung's Article Redemption Ideas in Alchemy, 1937 (Box 13)
  - Jung, C. G. (Box 13)
    - Death, 1961 (Box 13)
    - Lectures, 1936-1937, 1953 (Box 13)
    - Writings about Jung, 1946, 1956-1961, 1975 (Box 13)
    - Writings by Jung, 1916, 1948-1955, 1962, 1977 (Box 13)
  - Medical license, 1951 See Container OV 1, same heading (Box OV 1)
  - Reading courses (Box 14)
    - "Jung's Visions Seminars," 1977-1978 (Box 14)
    - "Readings II," The Collected Works of C. G. Jung, vols. 5, 11, 12, 13, and 16, 1973-1974 See also Container X 15, same heading (Box 14)
    - "Readings III," Mysterium Coniunctionis and Answer to Job, 1974-1975 (Box 14)
  - A Report on the First Twelve Years, 1948-1960, C. G. Jung Institute, Zurich, Switzerland, 1960 (Box 14)
  - Society of Jungian Analysts of Southern California, certificate of membership, 1980 See Container OV 1, same heading (Box OV 1)
  - Writings by Edinger (Box 14)
    - Anatomy of the Psyche, illustrations, circa 1985 (Box 14)
    - Psychological Approach to Gnosticism and Early Christiantiy, book chapters 7-12 and bibliography, undated (Box 14)
    - "Ralph Waldo Emerson: Naturalist of the Soul," article, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Writings by others, 1907, 1945-1964, 1971-1980, 1988, 2003 (Box 14)
    - Folder 1 (Box 14)
    - Folder 2 (Box 14)
    - Folder 3 (Box 14)
- 2021 Addition, correspondence, 1993 (Box 14)
- Closed (Box X 15)
  - Patient notes removed from reading courses, "Reading II," The Collected Works of C. G. Jung, vols. 5, 11, 12, 13, and 16, 1973-1974 (Container 14, same heading) (Box X 15)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Medical license, 1951 (Container 13, same heading) (Box OV 1)
  - Society of Jungian Analysts of Southern California, certificate of membership, 1980 (Container 14, same heading) (Box OV 1)